โอเค Bryan คุณช่วย
เริ่มต้นและบางทีแนะนำตัวให้พวกเรา
รู้จักชื่อคุณ ตำแหน่งของคุณที่ Acala
อาศัยอยู่ที่ไหนและทำงานจากที่ไหน?
ได้เลย ฉัน Bryan Chen ฉัน
อาศัยอยู่ที่ Oakland ประเทศ นิวซีแลนด์
ฉันเป็น CTO และ
เป็นผู้ร่วมก่อตั้ง Acala
เจ๋ง ฉันจะถามคุณเกี่ยวกับเรื่องส่วนตัว
ซัก2-3คำถาม เพื่อให้พวกเรา
รู้เกี่ยวกับคุณมากขึ้น
คุณช่วยบอกผู้คนว่าเมื่อ
คุณไม่ได้เขียนโค้ด
หรือสร้าง
สิ่งต่างๆบน Acala
คุณชอบทำอะไรเมื่อคุณมีเวลาว่าง
ในเวลาว่างที่เยอะมากของฉัน ฉันชอบที่
จะเขียนโค้ด
หรืออ่านสิ่งใหม่ๆ เพื่อ
เรียนรู้สิ่งใหม่ๆ ดังนั้น
ไม่ใช่แค่เขียนโค้ด
ฉันมักใช้เวลาค่อนข้างมาก
กับการเรียนรู้ เช่นภาษาโปรแกรมมิ่ง
ใหม่อันอื่นๆและ
เทคโนโลยีใหม่ๆและ
การค้นหาข่าวของแฮกเกอร์
เพื่อค้นหาสิ่งที่น่าสนใจ
ดังนั้น
ฉันอาจจะใช้เวลาเป็นส่วนมาก
กับกิจกรรมพวกนั้น แต่นอกเหนือ
จากนั้น ฉันเล่นเกมบ้าง
เล่นเกม PS ฉัน
ใช้เวลากับมัน ฉันมี
Nintendo Switch
ฉันก็ใช้เวลากับมันเหมือนกัน
ถ้าฉันต้องเลือก
ว่าที่ไหนที่ฉันจะใช้เวลาว่าง
2อย่างที่บอกไปจะเป็นส่วนใหญ่
เขียนโค้ด เรียนรู้ และ เล่นเกม
เจ๋งเลย งั้นช่วยบอกบางอย่าง
เกี่ยวกับคุณ บางทีเป็นบางสิ่งที่คุณ
ทำสำเร็จแล้วในอดีตหรือบางสิ่ง
ที่สนใจที่ผู้คนยังไม่รู้เกี่ยวกับคุณ
อืมม
ชีวิตฉันไม่ค่อยน่าตื่นเต้น
ซักเท่าไหร่
ฉันเกิดที่
ประเทศจีน
และย้ายมาที่ นิวซีแลนด์เมื่อฉันอายุ 13 ปี
ฉันเข้าเรียนมัธยม
เข้าเรียนมหาลัย
ทุกๆงานของฉัน
เกี่ยวกับโปรแกรมมิ่ง และเขียนซอร์ฟแวร์
สำหรับ startup
ค่อนข้างธรรมดา
ไม่มีอะไร
น่าตื่นเต้น
อะไรคือ startup แรกของคุณ
Laminar คืออันแรก ฉันเป็น
ผู้ร่วมก่อตั้ง ส่วน
อันอื่นๆฉัน
เป็นแค่พนักงาน
startup แรกที่ฉันร่วมงาน
ด้วยจริงๆแล้วก่อตั้งโดยเพื่อนฉันและ
เพื่อนร่วมห้องที่
มหาลัย Auckland พวกเขามีไอเดีย
เป็นโปรเจ็คจบของพวกเขา
จากนั้นพวกเขานำไอเดียไปสร้าง
startup ขึ้นมา มันค่อนข้าง
น่าสนใจ มัน
ชื่อว่า Kami มัน
เป็นเว็ปแอปคำอธิบายประกอบ PDF
มันเริ่มที่จะโตเพราะ
ช่วงนี้มีโควิด
เนื่องจากโควิด เพราะว่าผู้คนต้อง
เรียน
ที่บ้านและมีโฮมสคูล
มากมาย ดังนั้น
เครื่องมือนั้นจะมีประโยชน์ทีเดียว
ดังนั้น ใช่ ฉันทำงานที่แรกที่นั่น
นั่นคือ
เวลาที่ฉันได้เรียนรู้
หลายๆอย่าง
โดยเฉพาะเกี่ยวกับ startup
เอาละมาดูคำถามกัน คำถามที่น่าสนใจ
นั่นฉัน
ได้รับมาจาก Tim Ferris หนึ่งใน
podcast ที่ฉันฟังอยู่
คำถามนี้คือ: "ถ้าคุณมีป้าย
โฆษณาขนาดใหญ่ยักษ์ที่
ผู้คนอีกพันล้านจะเห็นมัน คุณจะเขียนอะไร
ลงไปบนป้ายนั้น
ข้อความอะไรที่คุณจะบอกผู้คน"
สิ่งแรกที่เข้ามาในหัวฉันคือ"ซื้อ
Bitcoin"
ใช่เลย นั่นดีมาก
คงจะดีไม่น้อย
ถ้าป้ายนั้นอยู่ในปี 2010
ฉันรู้ว่าคุณพูดถึงโค้ด
คุณเรียนรู้เยอะมากและคุณ
เล่นเกม บางที่นี่อาจจะได้คำตอบเหมือนเดิม
เมื่อคุณรู้สึกเครียดหรือไม่โฟกัสและคุณ
ต้องการ
ทางออก
คุณมีวิธีการ
รับมืออย่างไรกับมัน
ฉันบอกเลยว่าฉันทำงานหนักมาก
แต่ฉันก็ล้มเหลวเช่นกัน
เมื่อฉันไม่สามารถผลิตผลงานได้ ฉันจะ
หยุดทำงาน
ซักแปป
ฉันจะทำสิ่งอื่นซึ่งอาจจะเป็น
ดูยูทูป
เล่นเกม
ที่
ทำให้ฉันไม่ต้องคิด
ไม่มีกลยุทธ์ที่จะใช้
สำหรับฉัน ดังนั้นแค่ผ่อนคลาย
กับเกม ดังนั้นฉันแค่
ทำบางอย่างที่ไม่ต้องคิด
เกี่ยวกับปัญหา
ใช่เลย เยี่ยม
โอเค เรามาเข้าเรื่องเกี่ยวกับตำแหน่งคุณดีกว่า
คุณบอกว่า
ในอดีตคุณย้ายมาที่นิวซีแลนด์
ทำงาน startup
คุณช่วยบอกเราซักนิดว่า
อะไรที่ทำให้คุณเข้ามาสู่บล็อกเชน
และคริปโต
และอะไรทำให้คุณมาสร้าง Laminar
และ Acala
ฉันจำไม่ได้
ว่าเมื่อไหร่ที่ฉันได้ยิน Bitcoin แต่มัน
มาจากบางที่เมื่อตอนที่ฉันยังเรียนมหาลัย ดังนั้น
หลายปีแล้ว ครั้งแรกที่ฉันได้รู้จัก
Bitcoin
ฉันได้ยินมันเป็นประมาณเงินสดดิจิตอล
นั่นมันค่อนข้างแรกเริ่มมากๆ ความจริงแล้ว
มี
เรื่องราวเมื่อก่อนฉันต้องบอกคุณก่อน
เมื่อฉันอยู่มัธยม
ตอนยังเด็ก พ่อแม่ฉัน
ให้เงินฉันไม่ค่อยมาก
เด็กหลายคนพยายาม
หาทางที่จะหาเงินเพื่อให้เราสามารถ
ซื้อสิ่งที่เราอยากได้ได้
ในฐานะเด็กคอมพิวเตอร์
คุณต้องเข้า
ไปในอินเทอร์เน็ต กูเกิ้ลว่า"วิธีหาเงิน
ด้วยคอมพิวเตอร์"
มีซอร์ฟแวร์ ฉัน
จำชื่อไม่ได้
แต่
คุณสามารถดาวน์โหลด มันอาจจะ
มาจากการค้นคว้า
ในแล็บ หรือบางมหาลัย ถ้าคุณรันซอร์ฟแวร์
เพื่อหาข้อผิดพลาดบางอย่างใน
คอมพิวเตอร์ของคุณ
เพื่อคำนวณมันออกมา คุณ
สามารถหาเงินได้
โดยแค่เปิดซอร์ฟแวร์ คุณหาเงินได้
มันดูดีใช่ไหม ดังนั้นฉัน
จึงลงโปรแกรมและ
หลังจากนั้นไม่กี่เดือน
ฉันได้รับ
5 ดอลลาร์ จากนั้นแม่ฉันพูดว่า
"ทำไมบิลค่าอินเทอร์เน็ตและค่าไฟ
เดือนนี้ถึงแพงนัก"
ฉันรู้ทันทีว่ามันไม่ใช่ไอเดียที่ดี
นี่คือเรื่องราวในอดีต
หลังจากนั้นไม่กี่ปี ฉันเห็น
Bitcoin พูดว่า: ดาวน์โหลด
โปรแกรม
เปิดมัน และคุณจะทำเงินได้ ใช่ไหม
นี่คือสิ่งเดียวกันกับที่ได้เคยได้ยินและทำมัน
มาก่อน
ซึ่งพิสูจน์แล้วว่ามันไม่คุ้ม
ดังนั้นฉันพลาดโอกาสที่จะ
กลายเป็น miner นั่น
อาจจะเป็นหนึ่งในสิ่งที่ฉันเสียใจที่สุด
เมื่อไหร่?
เมื่อตอนฉันอยู่มหาลัย
บางทีอาจจะ 2009
หรือ 2010
ว้าว ช่วงนั้น Bitcoin พึ่งจะมีเอง
ใช่ พึ่งมี
ฉันพลาดโอกาสที่จะกลายเป็น
miner ในยุคแรกๆ ฉันไม่ได้
อ่านให้ดีเกี่ยวกับ Bitcoin หลังจากนั้น
ฉันแค่คิดว่า โอ้ฉันมี
Paypal เรามี Alipay
นั่นคือเงินบนอินเทอร์เน็ต คุณสามารถ
ส่งเงินนั้นบนอินเทอร์เน็ตง่ายดาย
ทำไมเราต้องการอย่างอื่นอีก
หลังจากนั้นหลายปี
ช่วงที่ Bitcoin
พุ่งขึ้นมา
และเมื่อช่วงที่ Bitcoin อยู่ในหน้าหนังสือพิมพ์
ฉันเรียนเกี่ยวกับมันอีกครั้ง
เพื่อนร่วมงานของฉันก็มี
Bitcoin และเขาคุยกับฉัน
เกี่ยวกับมัน
ผู้คน
เซอร์ไพรซ์ที่
เมื่อพวกเขาเพิ่มราคา
มันไม่ควรจะมากกว่าเดิม
When you cut something,
the price should be the same.
The Bitcoin cash fork proved that's
wrong on
internet or on blockchain.
The Bitcoin fork
and then combined value of both is
much higher than
original value and this was quite
interesting. That was the thing that
got me looking into bitcoin
again.
I was previously following
Bitcoin, but just reading it,
I never actually thought about buying it.
But this event got
me more interesting, so I considered
that maybe I should buy some.
Of course, you really
would have the motivation to study all
these things if you have your stake
into it. it's not a big stake but of
course it's some stake. Then I
spent more time researching,
reading
Bitcoin news and
actually spent time in
reading the bitcoin white paper, reading
all those new technologies.
I started thinking that
this could change
everything!
I guess
that led to your path of
of Co-founding Laminar and Acala?
Yes, that made me think
that
I really wanted to work in this industry
I spent more time
understanding the low-level thing, how it
actually works
and think about if I am
the guy
designing the things, then how I want to
design those things?
I started thinking about those things.
Cool.
I know we're all working
really hard right now, and we will
be for the foreseeable future, but
when you do have late
nights and early mornings,
what would you say is your
inspiration to keep
going? What's your
ultimate goal?
I like to build stuff. I like to
see
the stuff I have been working on.
In my previous job, I helped
build a product series, see it launched and
see how it's helping people. It's really
making things better
and improving people's lives. But,
working on a particular software
industry, then you probably improve a
small set of people,
but on blockchain I can see the
chance of
almost improving and changing the life
of everyone.
This is a very different
scale. There are
more possibilities.
Many years ago,
I was just thinking "oh maybe one day i
can do this", but now
it's different. I'm actually
pushing us forwards.
It's just a totally different
feeling.
Yeah, totally agree.
Let's move on to Acala
and Karura now. The first couple are
very short questions. Could you
describe Acala
in three words? Polkadot DeFi Hub.
That's good! Could you
describe Karura in three words?
Well, Kusama DeFi Hub.
Maybe could you tell us about
how Acala started and what the story is
behind?
How the teams met and how that
all came together?
So initially me,
Ruitao and Bette co-founded Laminar.
Ruitao had a lot of
connections and
experience on the Forex market. We're
thinking maybe building something
on this area and we also all believed
that DeFi would be the next thing that'd
go to take off. That's before
for example the compound
and issue.com token that actually started
the DeFi.
Back then, when we were
thinking that we wanted to build something
on DeFi, we
did some research and we figured
Substrate was/is the best blockchain
building framework and obviously the
Polkadot shared security
also solves a lot of problems for us.
I always said to
build with Polkadot on DeFi and maybe something
with
Forex market, so there will be sensitive
assets margin trading.
That's the background of Laminar.
When we designed the Laminar protocol,
we built a prototype on
Ethereum
that is depending on DAI as the
current source, as USD, and it's also
using compound as a money market.
Then we want to build a
similar thing on
Polkadot. We see this one
fundamental
dependency we need to have is a stablecoin.
So we figure we can either build a
stablecoin ourself
or maybe we can see if anyone else is
building a stablecoin
and use the stablecoin. But by then,
because we are very early,
there's no one who's actually building
a stablecoin.
So then we thought,
if some other people want to build a
stablecoin, we can maybe build it
together.
That was our thought process and,
in September 2019,
there was the
the first ever Substrate hackathon,
hosted by PolkaWorld,
in Hangzhou in China.
I was invited as a judge
for the hackathon.
Me, Ruitao and Bette flew
there.
We met a lot of people there.
I was
very active on a lot of chinese
Polkadot
community, but, you know, I'm in New Zealand
and they are in China so we never
saw each other face-to-face.
That was the first time
I saw a lot of people face-to-face
That was also the time when we met
Fuyao.
We've known Fuyao for quite a while,
because he created the
Polkawallet, the very first
mobile world app for Polkadot. It is one of the
first things built on the Polkadot
Substrate.
So we met Fuyao and his team.
They joined
the hackathon.
So we saw the energy
that they really wanted to build
something new to break or solve all
those
problems we have in the current
society.
You can see he has a really big
energy and big passion about it
and so we talked with each other.
They had already created
a Polkawallet
product but they're also thinking about
building a stablecoin
as well.
If they wanted to build a
stablecoin, we want to build a stablecoin,
maybe we could try to build it together!
That is kind of the
how the founders of Acala met and how
we
started this journey.
Then after this hackathon,
we're back to New Zealand and they went
back to Shanghai.
Then we started,
as Bette would say, "cold-dating for females".
So we just
started trying to work together
to
have daily stand-ups and just build the
thing
and see if everything
would work out.
It ended up being pretty well. We
enjoyed working with each other and we
managed not to have
too much issue size,
because we had two things
in two parts of growth but we didn't have
a lot of time. For example the typical
remote
working issues. It went all
very well.
That's how it all started. Cool.
When you're talking to potential future
developers to join your team,
how would you describe the culture
of working at Acala and what types of
technical characteristics but
also what type of
personality characteristics do you look
for
in potential hires?
Working in the blockchain space is
a bleeding-edge technology sector, so
you need to be very motivated,
because
things change every day. I know a
lot of people
that learn Substrate, they try to work on
Substrate but
there are so many new things coming up
every day that you need to constantly
adapt your code with the latest
change, because otherwise
almost daily or weekly
if you don't update Substrate, everything
breaks and falls apart.
There's a big frustration there,
but you need to get over it,
you need to get used to it and then you
need to be
already motivated to learn the new
things. You should be able to understand
why things break, you should not
get frustrated "Oh this doesn't work,
then I need to fix it again!". You should see it
as "well let's introduce a new feature, I can
do those things that previously were not
possible."
That's why we want people who
constantly want to learn new things,
because there are a lot of new things
out there every day and I want people
that are
also goal-orientated.
The goal is "get things done",
not just sitting in front of the computer typing
eight hours a day.
We don't want you to
just sit in front of the computer typing
but actually doing anything
productive, because this is
meaningless!
We want to just get things done.
Different people have different ways and
we
would like you to use the most
productive ways for you.
For example, some people
they enjoy working from home,
some people
prefer to
work at night. That's fine, as long as
things get done,
I'm happy.
As we are a remote team, we
have people all over the world,
so communication is a super important
piece,
a super important skill you must possess.
Some people will maybe
need a week get something done,
and
present the thing and other are
kind of fine with that.
During this absent period,
some people might
question or say "are you really
doing anything?" This attitude
doesn't help. So communication
is a very important skill.
Another thing I don't want to see is
that some people get stuck
and they try to fix the problem, but they
just spend
a long time trying to fix a problem and
that isn't very productive.
So you should be open-minded and
simply be able to ask for help.
Feel free to ask for help.
Maybe we cannot help, in that case
you just need to spend more time
trying to fix it, but
there's a chance that someone else is
able to offer a different opinion,
maybe they have seen this issue
before.
Communication is
also first, so important.
What types of people are you
looking for right now? I know we've got a
few roles
posted. Yes, we're
looking for different areas and
positions. For example,
we're definitely looking for Runtime
Substrate developers,
helping to build the core products, the
blockchain nodes
implement new pallets, improve existing
pallets and maintain them.
We're also looking for the Solidity
developers because we have the Acala EVM,
which is a very unique EVM. It's unlike
other
standard EVMs. We have done a lot of
modifications, introduced new features
and made adjustments. So we will need
Solidity developers to
help us to shape this; also to help other
things like building
and deploying the smart contracts on
the Acala EVM, to help to shape the
the contracts, to take
most advantage of the
unique features of
Acala EVM.
We need Solidity developers for
this and we also need
the front and back and full stack
developers
because obviously we have a lot of frontend
we need to build.
We already have the depth
but
we also have a lot of new things in the
plan. We also for example need
some nice governance, UI. We also
probably need some nice dashboards UI.
There's a lot of front-end work
waiting to be completed.
We are also looking for tech
educators,
because we have a lot of new unique
features, especially for Acala EVM.
So we would like to have someone who's able
to help us
write documentations examples and
tutorials in order to help
other developers to learn the
advantage and how to
integrate with Acala or learn how to
deploy the smart contracts or migrate
the smart contracts
and getting deployed to Acala EVM.
Okay great. Just a few more questions.
What would you say makes the Acala and
Karura team
unique and special to you?
First, I think
all of our team members are
at least
10 x engineers.
We all work very hard and we
all
are very keen to learn new things. We
are not afraid of
being blocked, not afraid of deep dive
into the code base to the low
level of
things, to
debug why things don't work.
This is
a very important mindset. We're
all willing to
go to the bleeding edge and pushing it
forward.
For us it is very important to expand.
If you were to pick
one product that you're
building
with Acala and Karura, what would you say
you're most excited about
and why is that?
I think Acala EVM will be
a super exciting product because
that is not built for us. It's built for
the developers, it's built for
other projects.
We will hopefully see a lot of
projects
either migrate from existing
smart contracts to Acala EVM, or just
develop for some
brand new smart contracts for Acala EVM.
We have a lot of unique features
that
don't exist elsewhere, like for example
the scheduler which allows a smart contract to
be
scheduled, to be called later.
On Ethereum people need to either rely
on centralized servers for them or
they need to design some super
complex
expensive token economics to make sure
it's happening.
This is just basically solved with
the building scheduler. There are a lot
more new possibilities
coming up and I'm really excited.
I look forward to see
how other people can leverage on all these
new features and
build something new.
Awesome. Last question:
so you're building a lot of these
DeFi products but if you think
like maybe five years in the future,
where do you see
all of this going and where do you
see Acala and Karura playing in that
story? Finance is a concept that exists
since I don't know how many years,
it probably started when
humans started trading. So it must be a
few thousand years already.
This is never going to die.
I would say in another thousand years from now,
there will be still finance systems.
That's obvious.
I
100% believe the DeFi will be
very strong
and much much stronger than today,
in maybe five years from now. Hopefully
DeFi will be able to become
the mainstream finance, so people will
see
the different ways to doing things,
you don't have to rely on centralized
banks,
financial service.
There is a decentralized service that is
much cheaper, it's much faster, it's much
more secure.
I'm hoping we can see this
completely shaping the industries and
also other industries,
because almost every other industry is directly
or indirectly
depending on the financial industry.
Maybe in few years, when the DeFi
is becoming mainstream, the other
industry people,
instead of using the traditional
centralized
financial service, they will start using
the DeFi
to help shaping the products, to manage
their company for example.
They don't need to be a decentralized
product, it could be a centralized
protocol but still benefiting
from DeFi.
Awesome. That's all the questions I
had. I
appreciate the time. Thanks.
I also enjoyed
present my mind to people.